Guide to the Karl Menger Papers, 1872-2000 RL.00888
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Karl Menger papers
1872-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Menger, Karl, 1902-1985
RL.00888
49 Linear Feet 29,500 items
Collection includes correspondence, notebooks, research and teaching notes, drafts of unpublished and published works, teaching materials, student theses, printed materials, and a few photographs. Mathematical subjects include curves theory, algebra, geometry, and the philosophy of mathematics. Many letters are from notable scientists; those written to Menger during World War II often comment on the hardships of colleagues still in Europe. Includes biographical materials relating to Karl Menger and to his father, the Austrian economist Carl Menger, and materials related to the history of the Vienna Circle (1920s-1930s), a group of scholars concerned with philosophy and science. Notebooks relate to Menger's early work as a student, and later notes on mathematical theory. Printed items include many European and American scientific reprints, textbooks, study manuals, and school publications.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Karl Menger Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1995.
Biographical note
Karl Menger (1902-1985) was an Austrian-American mathematician and professor, and was the son of economist Carl Menger.
1902: Born in Vienna 1920-1924: Studied at the University of Vienna; Ph.D. in Mathematics 1925-1927: Docent at the University of Amsterdam 1927-1936: Professor of geometry at the University of Vienna. Member of the Vienna Circle. 1930-1931: Visiting lecturer at Harvard University and The Rice Institute 1931-1937: Founder of Ergebnisse eines Mathmatischen Kolloquiums 1935: Married Hilda Axamit 1937-1946: Professor of mathematics, University of Notre Dame. Founder of Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, 2nd Series, and Notre Dame Mathematical Lectures 1946-1971: Professor of mathematics, Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago 1951: Visiting lecturer at the Sorbonne, Paris 1961: Guest lecturer at several European universities 1964: Visiting professor, University of Arizona and Ford Institute, Vienna 1968: Visiting professor, Middle East Technical Institute, Ankara 1971: Professor emeritus, IIT 1975: Austrian Cross of Honor for Science and Art First Class 1983: Doctorate of Humane Letters and Sciences, IIT 1985: Died in Highland Park, Illinois
Karl Menger (1902-1985) was an Austrian-American mathematician and professor, and was the son of economist Carl Menger.
Chronology
1902 Born in Vienna
1920-1924 Studied at the University of Vienna; Ph.D. in Mathematics
1925-1927 Docent at the University of Amsterdam
1927-1936 Professor of geometry at the University of Vienna. Member of the Vienna Circle.
1930-1931 Visiting lecturer at Harvard University and The Rice Institute
1931-1937 Founder of Ergebnisse eines Mathmatischen Kolloquiums
1935 Married Hilda Axamit
1937-1946 Professor of mathematics, University of Notre Dame. Founder of Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, 2nd Series, and Notre Dame Mathematical Lectures
1946-1971 Professor of mathematics, Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago
1951 Visiting lecturer at the Sorbonne, Paris
1961 Guest lecturer at several European universities
1964 Visiting professor, University of Arizona and Ford Institute, Vienna
1968 Visiting professor, Middle East Technical Institute, Ankara
1971 Professor emeritus, IIT
1975 Austrian Cross of Honor for Science and Art First Class
1983 Doctorate of Humane Letters and Sciences, IIT
1985 Died in Highland Park, Illinois
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, notebooks, research and teaching notes, drafts of unpublished and published works, teaching materials, student theses, printed materials, and a few photographs. Mathematical subjects include curves theory, algebra, geometry, and the philosophy of mathematics. Many letters are from notable scientists; those written to Menger during World War II often comment on the hardships of colleagues still in Europe. Includes biographical materials relating to Karl Menger and to his father, the Austrian economist Carl Menger, and materials related to the history of the Vienna Circle (1920s-1930s), a group of scholars concerned with philosophy and science. Notebooks relate to Menger's early work as a student, and later notes on mathematical theory. Printed items include many European and American scientific reprints, textbooks, study manuals, and school publications.
Germany -- History -- 1918-1933; Mathematicians -- Austria; Scientists -- Europe -- Correspondence; Germany -- History -- 1933-1945; Mathematicians -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Europe -- Emigration and immigration; Economists -- Austria -- Biography; Curves; Geometry; Economics -- History; Philosophy and science; Vienna circle -- History; Mathematics -- Study and teaching (Higher); Mathematics -- Philosophy; Algebra; Menger, Carl, 1840-1921; Menger, Karl, 1902-1985; Menger, Karl, 1902-1985; University of Notre Dame
- Correspondence Series, 1918-1984; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Correspondence Series has been arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with notes whenever possible indentifying individual correspondents and topics addressed in the letters.
  - Abbott, James C., 1943-1961 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    American mathematician. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Real projective geometry, hyperbolic geometry, Boolean algebra
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing, 1974 (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Publication of Menger's "The Foundations of Geometry"
  - Alexandroff, Paul, 1928 and undated (Box 1)
    Russian mathematician/topologist.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; some correspondence between Alexandroff and Hurewicz
  - Alexitis, Georges, 1933-1938 (Box 1)
    Hungarian mathematician.
    Topic(s): Dimension theory, combinatorial (algebraic) topology, calculus of variations, metric geometry; Brouwer, Urysohn; routine exchanges
  - Alt, Franz L., 1935-1962 and undated (Box 1)
    Austrian mathematician; student of Karl Menger and member of Menger's Mathematical Colloquium. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Calculus of variations, metric geometry; projective geometry; computer languages, progamming; routine exchanges; paper comments. Later correspondence in English
  - American Mathematical Monthly, 1954-1968 (Box 1)
    Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Author communiques, rejection letters
  - American Mathematical Society, 1953-1972 (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Author communiques, rejection letters; invitation to lecture
  - Aronszajn, Nachman, 1930-1948 (Box 1)
    Polish-American mathematician.
    Topic(s): Dimension theory, topology, theory of functions; routine exchanges
  - Arrow, Kenneth J., 1964-1972 (Box 1)
    American economist; 1972 Nobel Prize Winner in Economics.
    Topic(s): Arrow asks for K.M.'s input concerning the history of general equilibrium theory; Arrow's response to Menger's congratulations concerning Nobel Prize
  - Ayres, W.L., 1927-1930 and undated (Box 1)
    American mathematician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges
  - General correspondence, "A", 1938-1982 (Box 1)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with A. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Including: Mortimer J. Adler (thanks for reprint of "The New Logic"); Pier A. Abetti (routine exchanges); Lars V. Ahlfors (concerning K.M.'s notational suggestions); F. Axamit (routine exchange); Gordon Allen, M.D. (concerning K.M.'s notational suggestions); from K.M. to Richard T. Arnold (recommendation letter for Dr. Thomas Erber); Edward S. Allen (question about implication of "Moral, Wille,..."; Salvador Adora (routine exchange, thanks for financial help)
  - Bachiller, Tomás Rodriguez, 1935-1951 (Box 1)
    Spanish mathematician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; theory of functions, metric geometry
  - Bárány, Robert, 1920-1921 (Box 1)
    Austro-Hungarian otologist.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; Einstein
  - Behnke, Heinrich, 1965 (Box 1)
    German mathematician. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; theory of curves, dimension theory
  - Benedikt, Moritz, 1918-1926 (Box 1)
    Austro-Hungarian neurologist.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges (handwriting illegible)
  - Bentley, Arthur F., 1929 (Box 1)
    American political scientist.
    Topic(s): Set theory and number theory
  - Biedermann, M.M., 1926-1930 (Box 1)
    Dutch mathematician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges, thanks for reprints
  - Birkhoff, Garrett, 1938-1975 and undated (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Affine geometry, projective gemetry, lattice theory; history of dimension theory; routine exchanges; some correspondence between Garrett Birkhoff and H. Freudenthal
  - Birkhoff, George, 1935-1937 (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; some corespondence between George Birkhoff and Gottfried Haberler
  - Bloomfield, Leonard, 1937-1946 and undated (Box 1)
    American linguist.
    Topic(s): Projective geometry; routine exchanges, thanks for reprints
  - Blumenthal, Leonard M., 1931-1982 and undated (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Metric geometry, topology, calculus of variations; routine exchanges; discussion, planning of co-authored book ("Studies in Geometry," 1970)
  - Bocheński, Józef Maria, 1934-1955 (Box 1)
    Polish philosopher and logician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; modal logic, a formal-logical approach to ethical problems; Lukasiewicz
  - Bohr, Harald, 1926-1935 (Box 1)
    Danish mathematician; brother of Niels Bohr.
  - Bouligand, Georges, 1936-1959 (Box 1)
    French mathematician.
  - Bridgman, Percy W., 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    American physicist, 1946 Nobel Prize Winner in Physics. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Probabilistic analysis; Menger's Calculus textbook; routine exchanges, thanks for reprints
  - Brouwer, L.E.J., 1924-1930 (Box 1)
    Dutch mathematician and philosopher.
    Topic(s): Lengthy correspondence in German starting before and extending beyond Menger's time in Amsterdam as Brouwer's assistant.
  - General correspondence, "B", 1925-1980 and undated (Box 1)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with B. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Including: German philosopher, logician, and mathematician Oskar Becker (routine exchange); (Ludwig?) Bieberbach (postcard, routine exchange); (Otto?) Blumenthal (routine exchange); Karol Borsuk (paper submission? routine exchange); Paolo Bonetti (rejection letter from "Scientia"; Ruth Buschke (routine exchange); Émile Bréhier (newsletter from Neuvième Congrès International de Philosophie); Enea Bortolotti (routine exchange); Thomas J. Barry (publicity director for Notre Dame, request for photograph); G. van den Barren (? routine exchange); H.E. Bray (methods of proof in vector analysis); Egon Brunswick (probabilistic geometry); Reinhold Baer (projective geometry); Sister M. Francis Borgia, S.S.N.D. (proof of the sextuple theorem); H.L. Blackwell (from Menger, regarding probabilistic geometry, request for data); J.C. Boyce (incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding Menger's work at Argonne National Laboratory); Richard L. Baran (thanks for reprints); Stephen Baker (routine exchange); A.S.W. Borinski (regarding manusript sent by Borinski); Frederick Bock (request for correction of translated passage); Elizabeth Boyer (draft sent); Paul Bernays (comments on Menger's work?); Artur Bergmann (communication of mathematical results); Peter Benzin (request for comments ?); Donald R. Byrkit (request for help filling adjunct position at U. of West Florida); S. Bilinski (thanks for reprints); Leon Bernstein (routine exchange); William Bettelheim (regarding Carnap?); Margarete Boos (regarding Boos' attempt to write a biography of C. Menger); Father Baggio (correction of proof); Manuel Blum (automata theory)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1926-1939 (Box 1)
    German-American philosopher; member of Vienna Circle. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; Rockefeller Foundation funding; Carnap's work on logical syntax, principle of tolerance
  - Čech, Eduard, 1933-1935 and undated (Box 1)
    Czech mathematician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; request for Menger to guest lecture; Mathematical Colloquium; topology, set-theoretic geometry, calculus of variations
  - Chelsea Publishing Company, 1962-1973 (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Reprint of Menger's "Kurventheorie"
  - Cowles Commission, 1936-1937 (Box 1)
    Alfred Cowles 3rd.
    Topic(s): Third Annual (1937) Cowles Commission Resarch Conference in Economics and Statistics
  - General correspondence, "C", 1930-1977 and undated (Box 1)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with C.
    Including: Julian L. Coolidge (class scheduling for Menger's visiting semester at Harvard, 1930-31); Haskell B. Curry (request for letter of recommendation; reprints sent by Curry; mathematical logic); Alonzo Church (request for comments on Church's bibliography published in Journal of Symbolic Logic); Morris R. Cohen (regarding Rosenwald Foundation funding); H.S.M. Coxeter (routine exchanges, thanks for reprints; Coxeter's review of Abbott, Coxeter's comments on Menger's "Self-dual Postulates"); Rev. John J. Cavanaugh, C.S.C. (Notre Dame business; public lectures); Edwin Comfort (routine exchanges, reprints sent to Menger; AMS refereeing process); Alexander R. Craw (regarding reference to Menger in lecture by W.H. Huggins; routine exchanges); Thomas Cornides (reprints sent to Menger, routine exchanges); Robert S. Cohen (contract agreements); Harvey Cohn (mathematics education, pedagogy); Leslie Coghlan (request for reprints)
  - David van Dantzig, 1925-1928 and undated (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Constructivity, set theory; Brouwer's work on continuum
  - Dawson, John W., Jr., 1981-1984 (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Dawson's proposed biography of Gödel
  - DePauli-Schimanovich, Werner, 1981-1984 (Box 4)
    Author of "Kurt Gödel: Ein Mathematischer Mythos."
    Topic(s): Gödel; DePauli-Schimanovich's book on Gödel
  - General correspondence, "D", 1931-1983 and undated (Box 1)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with D.
    Including: Francois Divisia (routine exchange, lapsed correspondence; Econometric Society); Franz Deuticke (billing); William F. Dollar (possible purchase of Menger's philosophical library by Assumption University of Windsor, Canada); George B. Dantzig (reprints); Thomas R.A. Davis (request for evaluation of former research assistant); R.M. Dicker (offprints sent, thanks for offprints received); Leon M. Despres (financial matters); Ronald G. Douglas (routine exchange)
  - Errera, Alfred, 1937-1951 (Box 1)
    Belgian mathematician.
  - Evans, Griffith C., 1930-1938 (Box 1)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; publication in English of a summary of Menger's early work; invitation to Rice Institute; dimension theory; publication matters
  - General correspondence, "E", 1925-1958 (Box 1)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with E.
    Including: Paul Ehrenfest (routine exchange); Dimitry Egoroff (dimension theory); Howard S. Ellis (gold / monetary policy); B.Eckmann (request for Menger to lecture to Mathematical Colloquium of Zurich); Jack M. Elkin (mathematics education, pedagogy); Albert C. English (mathematics education, pedagogy); Florence L. Elder (thank you for visiting lecture)
  - Feigl, Georg, 1928-1930 (Box 2)
    German mathematician.
    Topic(s): Dimension theory; Jahrbuch über die Fortschritte der Mathematik
  - Feigl, Herbert, 1972 (Box 2)
    Austrian philosopher; member of the Vienna Circle.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges, Gödel, Wittgenstein, Russell, Vienna Circle
  - Flores, Antonio, 1934-1935 and undated (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Reprints, routine exchanges
  - Ford, Lester R., 1951-1957 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; I.I.T. business
  - Fraenkel, Abraham, 1928-1955 (Box 2)
    German-Israeli mathematician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; set theory, dimension theory, constructivity
  - Frank, Phillip, 1929-1952 and undated (Box 2)
    Austrian physicist, mathematician, and philosopher; member of the Vienna Circle.
    Topic(s): Suggested book for HUP on foundations of mathematics; program for "Kongress der Naturphilosophen"
  - Fréchet, Maurice René, 1936-1959 and undated (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Calculus of variations, probabilistic geometry; recommendation by Frechet of Menger for Fullbright Fellowship
  - W.H. Freeman and Company Publishers, 1962-1970 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Correspondence with publisher regarding geometry textbook co-written with Leonard Blumenthal
  - General correspondence, "F", 1926-1984 and undated (Box 2)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with F.
    Including: Robert Friedman (foundations of math, intuitionism, routine exchanges); Felix Frankel (routine exchanges, state of science and mathematics in Moscow ca. 1929, theory of curves); Leopold Fejér (routine exchanges); Ragnar Frisch (routine exchanges, request for Menger's writings on social-scientific applications of mathematics and logic); Simion Stoilow (regarding Hans Hahn); Ky Fan (routine exchanges, metric geometry); Robert Feys (routine exchanges, probability theory, modal logic); Paul Finsler (routine exchanges, thanks for reprints, invitation to Zurich Mathematical Colloquium); Herbert Amasa Forrester (copy of report sent to Menger); Henry George Forder (routine exchanges); Don C. Ferguson (request for Menger to review and evaluate Ferguson's "functional notation" for calculus); William J. Frascella (addressed to Marvin G. Mundt regarding history of analysis course); Alois Fritsch (routine exchanges); Solomon Feferman (thanks for reprints, John Dawson's biography of Kurt Gödel)
  - Ginn and Company Educational Publishers, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Correspondence regarding Menger's Calculus textbook
  - Gödel, Kurt, 1933-1972 (Box 2)
    Austrian-American logician, mathematician, and philosopher; associate of the Vienna Circle and member of Menger's Mathematical Colloquium.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges, mathematical logic, set theory, continuum hypothesis; Gödel's comments on Menger's work; request for news regarding Mathematical Colloquium; offer to bring Gödel to Notre Dame; Menger's Calculus textbook; mathematics pedagogy; Menger's request for Gödel's reminiscences of Vienna Circle; the extent of Wittgenstein's comprehension of Gödel's incompleteness theorems
  - General correspondence, "G", 1925-1981 (Box 2)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with G. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Including: Marcel Grossman (from Menger regarding metric geometry, postcard from Grossman to Menger); Harry Merrill Gehman (thanks for reprints; notification of Menger's appointment to American Association for the Advancement of Science); Heinrich Grell (invitation from Menger to speak to Mathematical Colloquium; post vist follow-up from Grell to Menger); Heinrich Gomperz (routine exchanges); Gerhard Gentzen (request for reprint); M. Gorce (request for reprint); Frau Gräfin (regarding translation of Menger's book); Lawrence M. Graves (routine exchanges, rejection letter from Bulletin of the AMS); Godofredo Garcia (routine exchanges); S. Grunzweig (routine exchanges); J. Trevino Garcia (request for reprints); Charles David Gorman (request for letter of recommendation); L.E. Grinter (request for Menger to join University of Florida faculty); Ferdinand Gonseth (invitation for Menger to attend meeting of International Congress for Philosophy of Science); Thomas L. Gilbert (critical comments on Menger's "What are Variables and Constants?"); Ralph J. Godzicki (communication of student praise of Menger); Dan Gottl (routine exchanges); James H. Bowden (to Martin Gardiner regarding Unexpected Hanging Paradox); Eugene T. Gadol (publication of Schilck volume); V. Grafe (routine exchanges); Roy Gunderson (request for letters of recommendation); Eugene Gehrig (thanks for reprints)
  - Haberler, Gottfried, 1983 and undated (Box 2)
    Austrian-American economist
    Topic(s): Comments on Carl Menger biography; thanks for reprints, Schumpeter, Birkhoff, Wassily Leontief, Böhm-Bawerk, Morgenstern; routine exchanges
  - Hahn, Hans, 1926-1931 and undated (Box 2)
    Austrian mathematician; Menger's teacher and founding member of the Vienna Circle.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; Brouwer, Urysohn, Birkhoff; set theory, geometry, topology (Hahn's handwriting mostly illegible)
  - Harlen, H., 1928 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Metric geometry, definition of convexivity, combinatorics; routine exchanges
  - Hart, John B., 1951-1975 (Box 2)
    American physicist.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges, request for reprints; Legendre transformation; relationship between Newton's first two laws of motion
  - Haupt, Otto, 1932-1963 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; theory of non-orientable manifolds
  - Hayden, Robert W., 1980-1981 and undated (Box 2)
    Topic(s): "New math" movement, Max Beberman, mathematics education / pedagogy; routine exchanges
  - Hayek, F.A., 1929-1983 and undated (Box 2)
    Austro-British economist and philosopher, 1974 Nobel Prize Winner in Economics. Folder includes some early correspondence between Hayek and J.M. Keynes.
    Topic(s): Correspondence between Hayek and Keynes concerns a potential position at the Bank of International Settlements and the possibility of Keynes recommending Hayek for such a position (Keynes treats Hayek's request cordially, but is rather non-committal), and a possible subscription by the Royal Economic Society to Carl Menger's Collected Works (which Hayek edited ?). Correspondence between Hayek and K. Menger addresses Wittgenstein (and Hayek's relationship with the latter); routine exchanges; Hayek raises the possibility that he and Menger were distantly related. Hayek offers comments on a biography of Carl Menger that Menger seems to have written at some point (?)
  - Heald, Henry T., 1951-1957 (Box 2)
    First President of Illinois Institute of Technology; later President of the Ford Foundation. Some outgoing correspondence
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges from Heald; letters from Menger concern mathematics education / pedagogy; some plea for funding from Ford Foundation for Menger's mathematics education project.
  - Hedrick, E.R., 1931-1937 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Resuest for Menger to lecture at Caltech, summer 1931, and at American Association for the Advancement of Science meeting in Denver, June 1937.
  - Holder-Pichler-Tempsky, 1964-1983 (Box 2)
    Viennese publishing company. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Licensing of Carl Menger's Grundsätze and Die Irrtümer; Menger's contribution to a monograph about Gödel.
  - Hurewicz, Witold, 1927-1929 and undated (Box 2)
    Polish mathematician.
    Topic(s): Metric geometry, dimension theory, set theory; Brouwer-Menger controversy; Urysohn, Alexandroff, Schreier, Kuratowski, Redeimeister; routine exchanges
  - General correspondence, "H", 1920-1983 and undated (Box 2)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with H. Some outgoing correspondence.